A Guide to the Papers of K. Edward Lay 1909-2004
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of K. Edward Lay1909-2004
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12817-c
1 arbitrary_unit
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the University of Virginia Library by K. Edward Lay, Cary D. Langhorne Professor of Architecture, University of Virginia, on January 14 and 28, 2005.
Scope and Content
This addition to the papers of University of Virginia Architecture Professor K. Edward Lay, ca. 1909-2004,ca. 2,500 items (9 boxes, ca. 4.5 linear feet) includes files on historic preservation consulting jobs; ca. 200 slides of architecture design studio projects; ca. 600 photographs of buildings in Albemarle County, Virginia and elsewhere; photographic files for Lay's article "European antecedents of 17th and 18th century Germanic and Scots-Irish architecture in America"; ca.1200 postcards and ca. 200 travel brochures and views, both chiefly of places in the United States.
In addition there are blueprints for Dalrymple House, Hillcrest Road, Elmira, New York, 1956, and Cumberland County, Pennsylvania, courthouse, 1959; a brass rubbing; photographs of sections, elevations and model of Stainback and Scribner's National Bank and Trust and recreation center for Charlottesville; videotape of Folly, Augusta County, Virginia, by Leigh Ann Johnson, 1994; audiocassette of interviews with Ernest Hoover and Mollie Van Allen on Nydrie and the architect D. Wiley Anderson, 1997; an audiocassette of a portion of an interview with Horace Burr while walking through Carrsgrove, including a discussion about the resident ghost, 1992.
Also present is a presentation book of work done by Lawrie & Green, Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, including Allen Junior High School, Camp Hill, Pennsylvania, Coatesville Junior High School, Coatesville, Pennsylvania, Office Building and Drug Store, Hershey, Pennsylvania, AMP Administration, Pine Street Elementary School, Palmyra, Pennsylvania, Susquehanna University Dormitories, Pennsylvania State Education Association Office Building, and Residence for Dr. and Mrs. George H. Fleming, Jr.
Arrangement
These papers are arranged in two series: Series I: Consulting, Topical and Research Files (Boxes 1-2) and Series II: Photographs, Postcards, and Travel Folders (Boxes 3-9), with the folders arranged alphabetically by heading within each series.
Contents List
- Series I: Consulting, Topical and Research Files
  - Albemarle County, Virginia- Articles and Clippings about buildings,2001-2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annadale Farm, Orange County, Virginia,1979, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Architecture Design Studio Projects- Slides,1969-1993, Ca. 200 slides. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Architectural drawings of Douglas M. Dalrymple House, Elmira, New York,1956 (Oversize 1)
  - Architectural drawings of Cumberland County Courthouse, Carlisle, Pennsylvania,1959 (Oversize 1)
  - Architectural drawings of Masonic Temple, Altoona, Pennsylvania,1989 (Oversize 1)
  - "Bear Castle," Louisa County, Virginia, and the Carr family,2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bel Aire (ca. 1820s), Albemarle County, Virginia,2001 October (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Buckingham County, Virginia- Articles and Clippings about buildings,1980, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cape Henry Lighthouse (1792), Virginia Beach, Virginia,1990 December, 1 of 2 folders. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cape Henry Lighthouse (1792), Virginia Beach, Virginia,1990 December, 2 of 2 folders. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Charlottesville Historic Landmarks Commission Awards,1980, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Cultural Resources Management of National Parks Services: Origins of Architecture School Artifacts,1997 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dauphin County Courthouse, Pennsylvania-Examples of "Old lettering,"n. d. (Oversize 1)
  - Edgewood, Amherst, Virginia,1988 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Foxwood and Springdale (ca. 1840), Goochland County, Virginia,1987 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Georgia Project- Architectural Preservation Report on the Sautee-Nacoochee Valley Preservation Study,1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Glen Wallace, Madison County, Virginia,1979 September 21 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Goochland County Court House, Goochland County, Virginia,1989 July 3 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Greene County House and Golden Hill, Greene County, Virginia,2004 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Jeffersonian Courthouse NHL Thematic Nomination Project(Draft) by Charles Brownell, Ph. D.,2003 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Keswick Farm (ca. 1825), Albemarle County, Virginia,2002 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Lamb Family House in Greene County, [Virginia]: A History by Ellen NicKenzie Lawson,2004 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - List of Student Papers done under Frederick D. Nichols [kept in University of Virginia Fine Arts Library ?],1994 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Map of Madison County, Virginia by Scheel,1984 (Oversize 1)
  - Marshall House (ca. 1745), Greene County, Virginia,1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Mayfield (ca. 1750), Petersburg, Virginia,1995 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Minor Family Pitcher (1821), Albemarle County, Virginia,2001 December (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Building Data,2001-2004 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Missing Acres, Albemarle County, Virginia,2001 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Mountain Grove (1803), Albemarle County, Virginia,2000 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - National Bank and Trust Company, Charlottesville Project, Stainback and Scribner, Architects (Not Built),1970 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - National Trust Historic Preservation Week Poster,1981 (Oversize 2)
  - Nelson County, Virginia,2002 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Orange Springs, Orange County, Virginia,1997-2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Patrick Manor, Albemarle County, Virginia,2000 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Petersburg, Virginia,n.d. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Piedmont, Albemarle County, Virginia,1936-2004 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Piedmont, Albemarle County, Virginia,1943-1944, 2 of 2 folders. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Plain View Farm, Albemarle County, Virginia,1994 November 10 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Presentation book of work done by Lawrie & Green, Harrisburg, Pennsylvania,ca. 1961-1963 (Oversize 2)
  - Recreation Center, City of Charlottesville Project, Stainback and Scribner, Architects (Not Built),1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Roland and Beverly Mill, Fauquier County, Virginia,1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Ross Stevens House, Sugar Hollow, Albemarle County, Virginia,2000 March (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Rubbing of a Knight,n.d. (Oversize 2)
  - Scottsville, Virginia- Articles and Clippings about buildings,2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Seay Estate (1851), Fluvanna County, Virginia,1999-2003 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Staunton, Virginia-Articles and Clippings about buildings, with copies of earlier correspondence,1995- 2004 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Strawberry Hill (1792), Petersburg, Virginia,1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Sunnyfields (ca. 1840), Albemarle County, Virginia,2002 February (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Tetley, Orange County, Virginia,2002 May (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Totier Creek Farm (ca. 1799), Albemarle County, Virginia,2002 February (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Virginia Historical Society,n.d. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Western View (ca. 1824), Fluvanna County, Virginia,2001 February (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Whitehall Farm, Albemarle County, Virginia,1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - William Newton Hale Exhibit Opening,2001 October 12 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Includes talk by K. Edward Lay.
  - Woodbourne, Madison County, Virginia,2002 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - World time zone map,n. d. (Oversize 2)
- Series II: Photographs, Postcards, and Travel Folders
  - Photographs for Article,European Antecedents of 17th & 18th Century Germanic and Scots-Irish Architecture in America, 1982, 1 of 5 folders. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs for Article,European Antecedents of 17th & 18th Century Germanic and Scots-Irish Architecture in America, 1982, 2 of 5 folders. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Photographs for Article,European Antecedents of 17th & 18th Century Germanic and Scots-Irish Architecture in America, 1982, 3 of 5 folders. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Photographs for Article,European Antecedents of 17th & 18th Century Germanic and Scots-Irish Architecture in America, 1982, 4 of 5 folders. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Photographs for Article,European Antecedents of 17th & 18th Century Germanic and Scots-Irish Architecture in America, 1982, 5 of 5 folders. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of Buildings,1997 October (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of Houses,2002 March (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of miscellaneous houses, etc.,2001-2002, 1 of 5 folders. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of miscellaneous houses, etc.,2001-2002, 2 of 5 folders. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of miscellaneous houses, etc.,2001-2002, 3 of 5 folders. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of miscellaneous houses, etc.,2001-2002, 4 of 5 folders. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of miscellaneous houses, etc.,2001-2002, 5 of 5 folders. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photographs- Navy Marine Corps Grants,n.d., 1 of 2 folders. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photographs- Navy Marine Corps Grants,n.d., 2 of 2 folders. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Postcards- Artwork & Specialty Cards,ca. 1909-1997 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Postcards- International- Mexico, Yugoslavia,n.d., 1986 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Postcards- United States- Alaska, Arkansas, Arizona,ca. 1950-1999 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Postcards- United States- California,ca. 1929-1991 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Postcards- United States- Colorado, Delaware,ca. 1952-1999 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Postcards- United States- Florida,ca. 1920-1996 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Postcards- United States- Georgia, Idaho, Indiana, Iowa,ca. 1946-2000 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Postcards- United States- Hawaii,1952 July, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Postcards- United States- Illinois, Kansas, Louisiana,ca. 1945-1988 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Postcards- United States- Maine, Maryland, Massachusetts,ca. 1937-2001 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Postcards- United States- Michigan, Mississippi, Missouri, Minnesota,ca. 1940-2000 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Postcards- United States- Montana, New Mexico, Nevada, North Carolina,ca. 1949-1990 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Postcards- United States- New Hampshire, New Jersey,ca. 1911-1998 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Postcards- United States- New York,ca. 1925-1993 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Postcards- United States- North Dakota, Ohio, Oregon,ca. 1925-2003 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Postcards- United States- Pennsylvania, pt. 1,ca. 1913-1993 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Postcards- United States- Pennsylvania, pt. 2,ca. 1919-1996 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Postcards- United States- Rhode Island, South Carolina, South Dakota, Tennessee,ca. 1949-1993 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Postcards- United States- Texas, Utah, Vermont,ca. 1946-1993 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Postcards- United States- Virginia,1995-2003 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Postcards- United States- Washington, Washington, D. C., Wisconsin,ca. 1934-1994 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Postcards- United States- Wyoming,n.d., 1952 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Travel Folders- United States- Arizona through New Hampshire,ca. 1925-1976, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Travel Folders- United States- New Jersey through Virginia,ca. 1937-1953, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Travel Folders and Post Cards- International,ca. 1948-1994, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 1)